Vitamin
-------

Library for easy rendering with opengl in Processing & Java


Current Version 0.5.5



TODO:
* Test setParameter for arrays with Cg and GLSL.
* Test RenderTarget2D as a RECT texture
* Test MRT class.
* (BoundingSphere)  Remove the sqrt from the calculations. that should speed up a bit.
* Add RemoveEffect( Effect ) to Timeline and EffectManager so effects can be removed correctly from the list.
* Add RenderTarget2D and RenderTarget3D classes that will work with render-to-texture
* Add MultipleRenderTarget2D for MRT's

FIX:
* (BoundingSphere)  Remove the sqrt from the calculations. that should speed up a bit.
- FIXED! NOTE! Method Circular blows up for some weird reason. Fix it or don't use it!!
- FIXED! NOTE! I've noticed that Expo interpolation mode, never really gets to the end value. few decimals away, 
  but its noticeable. BEWARE ON HOW TO USE IT!
	 
- Mesh: Commented code for 'Gram-Schmidt orthogonalize' on tangent vectors generation.
  what is being done is adding all tangents per vertex and normalized it in the end. should average it before the normalization
  FIX: implement tangent vector averaging for each vertex in the tangent vectors generation
- FIXED! create() and createData() methods from VTexture dont seem to be working. Do some more tests and see what is wrong
- FIXED! Textures are being loaded with color channels swapped. find out whats wrong.
  (Check VTexture formats or it could also be VImage loading channels and passing to VTexture with wrong information) 

















CHANGES:

( 2010-02-16 )
* Released version 0.5.5


( 2010-02-13 )
* (VTexture2D) New methods to accept VImage as input data to create a new opengl texture.
* Renamed VitaminMath Class from Math package to CommonMath. Seems more appropriate.
* Added ColorUtils class to Utils package. 
  Handle with low-level color stuff. Implemented methods to compute 32bit color int from R/G/B/A values



( 2010-01-28 )
* (ShaderCGFX) Working out a way to deal with effect parameters a la XNA



( 2010-01-24 )
* Created new class, MatrixUtils. Helpers for matrix handling and creation.
  createViewMatrixLH(), createViewMatrixRH(), getCubemapMatrix().



( 2010-01-19 )
* (StandardMaterial) Added methods to search for textures.
* (Material) Made class abstract.
  Changed material type flags to static integer. 





( 2010-01-19 )
* (Quaternion) Added new method to return a direction vector from a quaternion.





( 2010-01-18 )
* (VTextureCUBE) Added new loading method for one-texture, one cubemap. Loads a cross cubemap texture.




( 2010-01-13 )
(Shader)  Added new method setParameter1fv for linear arrays. 
(ShaderCGFX) Fixed bug with setParameter3/4fv. Now uploading arrays to shaders correctly.



( 2010-01-10 )
* Version 0.5.4 release!
* (Vtexture) Added new method getID(). I now prefer ID in capitals. Other methods are present as id() and getId().
* (ShaderCGFX) Changed/Added some methods.
  isPassValid() checks is current pass is a valid reference.
  resetAndGetNextPass() reset current pass and get next pass if available
  setTechnique() now returns CGpass.
  setPass(), nextPass() now returns current pass reference.
  Simplified getTechniqueFirstPass() method name to getFirstPass(). It also returns the current pass reference. useful for multipass effects.




( 2010-01-09 )
* (VGL) Implemented 2 new methods to pass 3/4 component vector arrays to shaders
  setParameter3fv()
  setParameter4fv()
* (RenderTarget2D) code revisited.


( 2010-01-02 )
* Added new method to Mesh class to compute edge list. #todo
* Added new class. MultiRenderTarget2D. Used for MRT, deferred shading, etc etc.  Needs testing



( 2009-12-27 )
* (VCamera) Added new method that accepts for camera Position/Target/Up as vectors.




( 2009-12-25 )
* (ImageUtils) Added new method to convert an HeightMap to a NormalMap of vectors.
* (Utils) Added new class ImageUtils.


( 2009-12-18 )
* Changed 'util' package name to 'utils'.



( 2009-12-13 )
* (Matrix) Added few set methods to take float/double arrays as parameters.


( 2009-12-11 )
* Renamed VMath to VitaminMath. Added few more methods to handle math calcs. 
  clamp( val, min, max ) - clamps a value to the given min/max parameters.
  makePerpendicular( src, dest ) create a perpendicular vector to the "src". If its not possible it returns false, else is true, and the perpendicular vector is on parameter "dest".
* (vitamin.util) Added new method for building stack lists, StackList<T>. Create a stack list of the defined type.
* (BoundingSphere) Implemented intersectRay() method.
* FIXME! (BoundingSphere)  Remove the sqrt from the calculations. that should speed up a bit.
* (Math) Added new method, IntersectionPoint. Wraps a point and a parametric time value. Useful for intersection computations.
* (Math) Added new method to FastMath. atan2Fast(y, x). Taken from JBullet project.
* (Math) Added new class FastMath. Holds methods with better performance for math calculations, eg. atan2(y,x)



( 2009-12-09 )
* Fixed minor bugs/features to the RenderTarget2D class.
* New class created vitamin.util.BufferUtils. Handy class used to create and handle native buffers.




( 2009-12-07 )
* (RenderTarget2D) Now FBO are working. Support for several 2D (POT & NPOT) surface formats.
  It always attaches a DepthStencil Buffer. FIXME! Might need to choose if needs a z-buffer or not.
  It saves current viewport when binding the RT, and restores it when unbind() is called.



( 2009-12-01 )
* (Matrix)  Added method to return translation vector.
* (Mesh)  computeNormals and computeTangents() now take a parameter to force/not force re-computation.
* (Mesh)  Changed method computeTBNMatrix() to computeTangents().


( 2009-11-26 )
* (Vector3)  New methods to accept float array as parameter.


( 2009-11-23 )
* Fixed bug with normals in drawGridXZ. Also added tangent vectors on GL_TEXTURE1.
* (Mesh)  Added AABB members to the mesh class.
* Added new classes for boundaries computation, BoundingBox and BoundingSphere.


( 2009-11-19 )
* (VStringUtils) New method dataPath() returns a string with the current directory.




( 2009-11-13 )
* (VCamera) Added new method to let user set the Up Vector.
* (VTexture2D) Added new method to support SamplerState as parameter. 
* Created new texture class, VTextureCUBE to load Cubemaps into opengl.


( 2009-11-11 )
* (Interpolation) Implemented a new interpolation mode, Smoothstep.


( 2009-11-05 )
* added new method - openFileChooser(...) - to VitaminUtils, to open a file from the drives, using JFileChooser.
* Created new class for utilities, VitaminUtils. Created new methods, getExtension(...).



( 2009-11-01 )
* VTimer: Changed timer to use nanoTime instead. Should have more precision.




( 2009-09-23 )
* Shader: implemented new method. setParameter2i().


( 2009-09-22 )
VGL: Changed method drawGrid(). Added new parameter to flip the normals.



( 2009-09-15 )
TimeSegment: Added new member called _resetTime. Used to reset the effect time or not.



( 2009-09-10 )
* New changed to EffectManager and Effect. Making it possible to support multiple time-segments.


( 2009-09-08 )
* Added 2 new methods to VGL.
  enableTexture( idx ). enables a textured created by VGL
  disableTexture(). disable texture mapping.

( 2009-09-04 )
* Added new constructors for VTexture2D.


( 2009-08-31 )
* Added support for multiple TimeSegments on the Effect class.
* EffectManager Render updated. it checks each effect at current time and see if it should be playing or not.


( 2009-08-22 )
* Changed code that used old Interpolation methods to the new ones.
* Implemented new package called Interpolation, based on Penner's easing library.
  Methods implemented: Linear, Quad, Cubic, Quart, Quint, Sine, Expo, Back, Bounce, Elastic, Circular


( 2009-08-18 )
* Vitamin now supports OpenGL Rectangle textures.
* New method added to VGL. enableTexture( boolean, textureType ). Set to use with NPOT textures
* Added new variable to VTexture to identify the type of texture. TEXTURE_1D, TEXTURE_2D, TEXTURE_RECTANGLE_2D, TEXTURE_3D 
* Added new constructor to VTextureRECT. VTextureRECT( GL, String); 
* Added new method to load images from file in VTextureRECT. Should make things easier for the user
* Extended new class from VTexture called VTextureRECT. loads rectangle textures in opengl.


( 2009-07-22 )
* Vitamin 0.5.1 released
 
 
 
( 2009-07-18 )
- Mesh: Commented code for 'Gram-Schmidt orthogonalize' on tangent vectors generation.
  TODO: implement tangent vector averaging for each vertex in the tangent vectors generation
- Scene: Removed the code used in Morphing Heart application from the framework. *pff* what an hack =)
- MeshSphere: Fixed problem with double vertex count. Still rendering isnt correct.
  FIXME: Compute a correct triangle list
- Mesh: Normals and Tangents were being re-processed. now its fixed using flag control 
  Added new method to render direct mesh data. Useful to render with shaders on applications, since Vitamin does not support shader materials

( 2009-07-17 )
- VTexture: Fixed problem with loading textures with no-mipmap option.

( 2009-07-15 )
- Matrix: Added getDoubleBuffer() method. Returns a DoubleBuffer

( 2009-07-14 )
- Vector3: Added distanteSqr() method. Computes squared distance between two points.
- TimelineLayer: Changed to support different interpolation methods: LINEAR + COSINE.
- Changed minor things in Timeline. Commented HashMap version, using Vectors. FIXME!
- EffectManager: Create new method process() to initialize all effects. This method should be called after adding all fx to the manager.

( 2009-07-14 )
- Created new classes, Timeline and TimelineLayer. This classes support handling variables during time of an application.
  Each layer holds a variable (Layer) with n'th values that are interpolated along the timeline.

( 2009-07-13 )
  NOTE! VGL has a texture pool. Use addTexture(), createTexture methods from VGL.
- VGL: Made width and height variable private. To access them use getWidth() and getHeight()
  Changed release() method to clear texturepool and shader pool. 
- Created 2 new classes. VTexture1D, VTexture2D. Should be self-explanatory.
- VTexture: Changed few methods names. Now constructor needs the target type as parameter. eg. VTexture( GL.GL_TEXTURE_2D, gl );

( 2009-07-12 )
- VMath: Added few more functions
- VTexture: Added createData() method. Loads and sets an opengl texture from an int array buffer


( 2009-07-02 )
- Matrix: Added a static method to compute inverse of matrices, inverse( dest, src )
- Math: Added clone method. does what it says.. clones an object
- Matrix, renamed matrix mul methods to mulRowMajor and mulColumnMajor


( 2009-06-05 )
- Added mulRotation(Matrix m) method do Matrix class. Multiplies only the rotation part of the matrices.

 
( 2009-06-04 )
- MMExp now exports morphing data. Should add it to MMLoader and make vitamin support animations.
- Added new class to math. Ray3. FIXME. write all methods to handle rays
- Added new class to math. Interpolation. Handles several methods to interpolate values
- Added new package called Shapes. Should include several shapes for easy setting and rendering. Triangle, Quad added
- Changed Mesh renderChunks to use a shader for rendering. this is an hack for render. FIXME


( 2009-04-28 )
- Added new image format to VImage - ABGR -. For some reason 32bit PNG's are being loaded as CUSTOM formats and with this format.
  Now they load correctly with correct channel position.


( 2009-04-27 )
- VParticleSystem changed to abstract. Other particle system should extend from this class.


( 2009-04-26 )
- VParticleSystem updated. Method update() and render() were created. Still needs alot of work ofcourse.
- getExtensions() method added to VGL. Returns a string of all supported extensions.
- VSamplerState updated to support 3D textures
- Added new create() method to VTexture for 3D textures creation.


( 2009-04-20 )
- Added Timeline to vitamin.fx package. 
  Needs some work to display all active fx plus info on them (time they are being played, etc).
- Implemented ShaderCG. to pass parameters one must use the setProgram() method so that parameters are passed to the current program
  Semantics aren't supported by ShaderCG.
- Fixed problems with scenesimple on rendering multimaterials. passed texture loading to Scene process() method, removed from MMLoader.
- VImage added. handles loading of images from the disk.
- VTexture works on VImage to load images
- VSamplerState created




--------------------------------------------------------------

vitamin.scenesimple.

support for multimaterials
support for hierarchy. only for mesh/helpers for now
Describes a simple 3d scene with hierarchy.


vitamin.scenegraph.

Describes a simple 3d scene in a graph relationship.
